{"tossups": [{"question": "In this city, Ezra Pound and Igor Stravinsky are buried on the island of San Michele. Operation Bowler targeted this city\u2019s harbor with a precision air strike. One traveler from this city was imprisoned in Genoa, where Rustichello da Pisa recorded his stories in<em> Il Milione</em>. The admirer of the Polish boy Tadzio, Gustav von Aschenbach, dies in this city in a 1912 novella by Thomas Mann. Marco Polo was from, for ten points, what Italian city, famous for its canals?", "answer": "<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Sigmund Rascher\u2019s experiments were used to test technology for this military force. Members of this group carried out the Stalag Luft III murders after a group of Allied POWs escaped from one of their prisons. Its leader committed suicide after being sentenced to death during the Nuremberg Trials. The Junkers [yoon-kers] Ju-87 was heavily used by this organization for dive-bombing. Herman Goering led, for ten points, what branch of the Nazi military that bombed Britain?", "answer": "<b> Luftwaffe</b> (accept the (Nazi)<b> German Air Force</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This individual earned a \u201cproduction E\u201d in a song by Redd Evans and John Jacob Loeb. This figure inspired a National Historical Park in Richmond, California that is home to the SS<em> Red Oak Victory</em>. Geraldine Doyle was the inspiration for one depiction of this character by Westinghouse employee J. Howard Miller, which depicts her with a red bandana and flexed bicep, saying \u201cWe Can Do It!\u201d for ten points, name this icon that encouraged American women to take factory jobs during World War II.", "answer": "<b> Rosie the Riveter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Battle of the Plains of Abraham was fought in what is now, for ten points, what namesake capital city of a French-speaking Canadian province?", "answer": "<b> Quebec</b> City", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Shortly after performing this action, one athlete, born Chris Jackson, was suspended by the NBA after refusing to stand for \u201cThe Star-Spangled Banner.\u201d The New York State Athletic Commission suspended one athlete for draft evasion, which that athlete justified on grounds of having performed this action. A Milwaukee Buck and future Laker changed his name from Lew Alcindor several years after performing this action, which includes reciting the shahada. For ten points, name this religious action performed by star athletes Kareem Abdul-Jabbar and Muhammad Ali.", "answer": "<b> convert</b>ing to<b> Islam</b> (or<b> becom(e)</b>ing a<b> Muslim</b> or equivalents) Page 1", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Russian Empire used Agvan Dorzhiev as a contact to one of these people. One of these people fled in response to a military expedition led by Francis Younghusband, and his successor called for a democratic \u201czone of peace\u201d in his Strasbourg proposal. These people are said to be reincarnations of Avalokitesvara, and the most recent of these people went to exile in India after a 1959 uprising was crushed by Chinese forces. For ten points, name this position currently held by Tenzin Gyatso, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.", "answer": "<b> Dalai Lama</b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "According to its invocation, this ruling was \u201csincerely believed to be an act of justice warranted by the Constitution.\u201d This ruling came with one hundred days\u2019 notice and specifically exempted New Orleans and the land that was to become West Virginia. The victory at Antietam led to its issuing, which only immediately took effect in territory controlled by Union forces. For ten points, name this executive order issued on January 1, 1863 by President Lincoln, which freed over three million slaves in the South.", "answer": "<b> Emancipation Proclamation</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man appointed Edward Douglass White as Chief Justice. He used the \u201cSaxbe fix\u201d to appoint Philander Knox, who carried out a program of promoting corporate interests in foreign countries, or\u201cdollar diplomacy.\u201d In his re-election campaign, he only won Utah and Vermont, partially because his predecessor split from the Republican Party to run on the Bull Moose ticket. For ten points, name this President who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt, then served as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.", "answer": "William Howard<b> Taft</b> <b>Second Quarter</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Akrotiri was destroyed by one of these events near what is now Cape Kolumbo. The ROTAS-SATOR and ROMA-MILO magic squares were discovered in the ruins of another of these events, from which Rectina was to be rescued from Stabiae by a fast ship commanded by Pliny the Elder. For ten points, name these devastating events that took place on Santorini circa 1500 BC, wiping out the Minoans, and on Vesuvius in 79 AD, destroying the town of Pompeii.", "answer": "volcanic<b> eruptions</b> (accept descriptions of<b> volcano</b>es)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This scientist invented the parallel linkage, found in some automobile axles. This scientist, along with his business partners Matthew Boulton and James Keir, developed a machine to copy ink documents. This scientist\u2019s separation of the condenser and cylinder in a previous invention developed by Thomas Newcomen allowed it to become the most widely used power source during the Industrial Revolution. For ten points, name this inventor of a rotary steam engine and the namesake of the SI unit for power.", "answer": "James<b> Watt</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {}, {"question": "In this battle, James Calhoun\u2019s men held high ground but lost their horses when their handlers were shot. Reports of incoming soldiers shortly before this battle were dismissed by the elder Runs the Enemy, who noted that Americans never attacked in midday. The death of the scout Bloody Knife triggered Marcus Reno\u2019s retreat from this battle, shortly before the 7th Cavalry was utterly destroyed. For ten points, name this June 1876 battle in which George Custer made his failed \u201clast stand.\u201d", "answer": "Battle of (the)<b> Little Bighorn</b> (or Battle of the<b> Greasy Grass</b>; accept<b> Custer\u2019s Last Stand</b> before Custer is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A call for the devolution of this region was suggested by the Kilbrandon Report and was opposed by Neil Kinnock in 1979. The Marcher Lords governed this nation\u2019s eastern border. In the early 1400\u2019s, Henry V subdued Owen (+) Glendower, a rebel from this nation. The titled ruler of this nation wears a badge with three white feathers, and a red (*) </b> dragon appears on this nation\u2019s flag over a white and green background. Llewellyn the Great once led, for ten points, what constituent country of the UK whose capital is Cardiff?", "answer": "<b> Wales</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Hans Oster plotted a coup d\u2019\u00b4etat if war with this country broke out. Political dissidents in this country met at the Magic Lantern theater, forming the Civic Forum. Charter 77 was signed by dissidents in this country, including (+) Jan Pato\u02c7cka [pa-totch-ka]. Gustav Husak led a period of normalization in this country, which underwent the (*) </b> Velvet Divorce under its last president, Vaclav Havel. For ten points, name this country that dissolved in 1993 into modern day components whose capitals are Bratislava and Prague.", "answer": "<b> Czechoslovakia</b> (do not accept or prompt on Czech Republic or Slovakia alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The Vela Incident was likely a result of one of these programs. One of these programs was exposed by</b><em><b> The Sunday Times</b></em><b> with the testimony of Mordechai Vanunu. South Africa</b> <b>was the first country to (+)</b> <b>voluntarily end one of these programs.</b> <b>Another of these</b> <b>programs carried out Operation Smiling Buddha, under the watch of Indira Gandhi. India, (*) </b> Pakistan, and Israel have refused to sign a treaty banning the proliferation of these programs. For ten points, name this type of military program, one of which claimed success in North Korea in January 2016.", "answer": "programs for the development of<b> nuclear weapon</b>s (accept any equivalent for nuclear weapons, including<b> hydrogen bomb</b> before mentioned; prompt on \u201cthe bomb;\u201d prompt on nuclear program; do not accept or prompt on nuclear energy programs)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The Navigation Acts supported this policy, for which Jean-Baptiste Colbert advocated</b> <b>as Louis XIV\u2019s Finance Minister. This practice\u2019s emphasis on (+)</b> <b>trade balance contrasts</b> <b>with the Physiocratic view that labor created national wealth. Colonial expansion and high (*) </b> tariffs were trademarks of, for ten points, what economic practice in which countries manipulated their economies to gain more monetary wealth than rival nations, which dominated Europe in the 17th and 18th centuries?", "answer": "<b> mercantilism</b> (accept<b> bullionism</b>) Page 9", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist used his son, Jarvis, as a model for Michael Schwerner in one work. Another work by this artist shows four U.S. Marshalls escorting six-year-old Ruby Bridges to an all-white school. This man\u2019s work for</b><em><b> LOOK</b></em><b> magazine include</b><em><b> Southern Justice</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> The</b></em> <b>(+)</b> <em><b>Problem We All Live With</b></em><b>, and he depicted a man dissenting at a town meeting and</b> <em><b>Problem We All Live With</b></em><b>, and he depicted a man dissenting at a town meeting and</b> <b>an old woman serving a turkey as part of a series inspired by (*)</b> <b>an old woman serving a turkey as part of a series inspired by (*)</b> FDR\u2019s 1941 State of the Union. For ten points, name this artist who illustrated the<em> Four Freedoms</em> series and many covers for the <em>Saturday Evening Post</em>.", "answer": "Norman<b> Rockwell</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The deciding vote for this amendment was cast by Harry Burn, a Tennessee legislator who was persuaded to \u201cput the rat in ratification.\u201d This amendment overruled</b><em><b> Minor v.</b></em> <em><b>Happersett</b></em><b>, and its ratification was upheld in (+)</b> <em><b>Leser v. Garnett</b></em><b>. This amendment was</b> <em><b>Leser v. Garnett</b></em><b>. This amendment was</b> <b>advocated for by the Silent Sentinels and a 1913 parade organized by (*)</b> <b>advocated for by the Silent Sentinels and a 1913 parade organized by (*)</b> Alice Paul, and was popularly named after one of its first proponents, Susan B. Anthony. For ten points, name this 1920 Constitutional amendment that granted women the right to vote.", "answer": "<b> 19</b>th Amendment", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>An autopsy on Henri Paul after this event showed anti-depressants and a blood-alcohol level triple the legal limit. Earl Spencer criticized the media for causing this event in a</b> <b>speech that uncharacteristically drew applause. The headline \u201cWhere is our (+)</b> <b>speech that uncharacteristically drew applause. The headline \u201cWhere is our (+)</b> <b>Queen?\u201d</b> <b>Queen?\u201d</b> <b>called out Elizabeth II for failing to return from Balmoral Castle after this event.</b> <b>called out Elizabeth II for failing to return from Balmoral Castle after this event.</b> <b>called out Elizabeth II for failing to return from Balmoral Castle after this event.</b> <b>Dodi</b> <b>Fayed was killed at the (*)</b> Pont de l\u2019Alma tunnel in this event, after which Elton John re-wrote Pont de l\u2019Alma tunnel in this event, after which Elton John re-wrote Pont de l\u2019Alma tunnel in this event, after which Elton John re-wrote \u201cCandle in the Wind\u201d. For ten points, name this 1997 event in which the former wife of Prince Charles was killed in a car crash.", "answer": "<b> death</b> of Princess<b> Di</b>ana (accept equivalents, such as the<b> car crash</b> that killed Princess<b> Di</b>ana)  Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}